So today's דף daf is ס"א, Samech Alef, sixty-one. We start at
the very bottom of ס"א עמוד ב'. Samech Amud Beis. What we're
dealing with is the debate between רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and רבי
נחמיה Rebbe Nechemia about where the order is מעכב. me'akev. According to
רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, the order is only מעכב me'akev in what
is done in the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, לבן בפנים. Lavan Bifnim.
According to רבי נחמיה, Rebbe Nechemia, the order is מעכב me'akev in
anything that's done בבגדי לבן, bebigdei Lavan, whether it's בפנים, bifnim, whether
it's בחוץ, bachutz, which is also the blood on the פרוכת, Parochet,
the blood on the מזבח, Mizbeach, also includes all of the stuff
that's done prior: the הגרלה, Hagrala, the shechting of the פר, par,
the shechting of the שעיר, se'ir, the taking of the קטורת, Ketoret,
everything that's done בבגדי לבן בחוץ. bebigdei Lavan bachutz. The one question
that came up is: does that also include the spilling of the
שיירים Shirayim that is done afterwards? How much is—and that turned into
a question of: normally the שיירים, Shirayim, the spilling of the remnants
of the blood, the pouring, is not מעכב, me'akev, but maybe by
יום כיפור Yom Kippur specifically because it says וכיליה מכפר, Vechilah Mechaper,
only when you complete everything, maybe the שיירים Shirayim is מעכב. me'akev.
So if doing the שיירים Shirayim is מעכב, me'akev, there are two
questions. Number one: is doing it מעכב? me'akev? If you didn't do
it, were you יוצא? yotzei? And number two: once you say if
it is מעכב, me'akev, then obviously it will be included in the
issue of where order matters. But so that was the issue. But
again, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda only order matters in there; רבי נחמיה
Rebbe Nechemia order matters everything that's done בבגדי לבן, bebigdei Lavan, even
בפנים, bifnim, בחוץ, bachutz, with the one question of שיירים Shirayim because
whether that is מעכב me'akev or not by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
So that is the debate. The one thing we have not addressed
is the other thing that's done בבגדי לבן בחוץ bebigdei Lavan bachutz
that we haven't got up to yet, which is the sending of
the שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir L'Azazel. That is also going to be done
בבגדי לבן בחוץ, bebigdei Lavan bachutz, but this is what we're talking
about.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: the גמרא Gemara just
yesterday also then had the statement of רבי חנינא. Rebbe Chanina. You
know what? Maybe we'll pick up with that because—but
so we'll go back a little bit. We'll go about eight lines
before the
דף daf ends, where there's an
asterisk right before the word רבי.
Rebbe. The asterisk, right, thank you. אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rebbe Chanina,
קטורת שחפנה קודם שחיטת פר לא עשה ולא כלום. Katoreth shechafna kodem
shechitas par lo asah v'lo kloom. So if you did the קטורת
Ketoret here, the חפינת קטורת chafinas Ketoret before you shecht the פר,
par, here's the order: you shecht the פר, par, you do the
הגרלה, Hagrala, then you do the קטורת, Ketoret, you bring the קטורת
Ketoret in, then you get the blood of the פר par from
here, you do the blood, then you shecht the goat, you do
the goat, and then you move out. So here the order first
is שחיטת פר, shechitas par, הגרלה, Hagrala, חפינת קטורת. chafinas Ketoret. If
you did the קטורת Ketoret before the shechting of the פר, par,
that's out of order; it doesn't count. Fine. That seems to be
רבי נחמיה, Rebbe Nechemia, right? רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemia is the one
that said everything order matters. That's רבי נחמיה. Rebbe Nechemia. רבי נחמיה
Rebbe Nechemia says it all, everything even בבגדי לבן, bebigdei Lavan, whether
it's בפנים, bifnim, whether it's בחוץ. bachutz. According to רבי יהודה, Rebbe
Yehuda,
if you do the חפינה chafina out of order, if you do
that out of order, then רבי נחמיה, Rebbe Nechemia, everything that was
subsequent to it doesn't count.
Well, no, it doesn't count. Let's make that clear. If you do
the חפינה, chafina, when you do something out of order, what doesn't
count is the thing—is the thing that you did earlier. So if
you did the חפינה chafina earlier, that didn't count. Now, if you
did the שחיטה shechta and the הגרלה Hagrala and then you went
to the שעיר, se'ir, thinking you had done the חפינה, chafina, now
you got a problem because now you did the שעיר se'ir before
you've done the legitimate חפינה. chafina. So but it'll have—it could have
a ripple effect. But the basic point is the thing you did
out of order doesn't count.
לא עשה ולא כלום Lo asah v'lo kloom
with the חפינה chafina itself. The thing itself is not legitimate. That
is if you do the חפינה chafina before the פר, par, the
חפינה chafina was no good. So that's something that's outside of the
קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So the גמרא Gemara says כמאן? k'man? Who
is that going like? דלא כרבי יהודה, d'lo k'Rebbe Yehuda, not like
רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. דאי רבי יהודה האמר כי כתיב חוקה בדברים
הנעשים בבגדי לבן מבפנים הוא דכתיב. de'ee Rebbe Yehuda ha'amar ki ksiva
chuka bidvarim hana'asim bebigdei Lavan mibifnim hu deksiva. No, it only applies—the
order—when it's stuff that's in the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, אפילו תימא רבי יהודה. afilu teima Rebbe Yehuda.
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda could agree. Why? צורך פנים כפנים דמי. tzorech
pnim kepnim dami. Now we are going to limit the extent of
the debate. That רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda doesn't just say here order
matters, it also matters everything that's done out here that's for the
sake of in here. What's done out here that's for the sake
of in here? Everything: the shechting of the פר, par, the הגרלה,
Hagrala, although we haven't really mentioned הגרלה, Hagrala, but whatever, presumably הגרלה,
Hagrala, right? The חפינת קטורת, chafinas Ketoret, the שחיטת השעיר, shechitas hase'ir,
everything there is necessary for in there. So now according to רבי
יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, it's this plus this is רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda.
So the only debate is six, seven, eight, and nine. When you
get to the blood on the פרוכת, Parochet, the blood on the
מזבח, Mizbeach, and maybe the שיירים. Shirayim. But now we're saying that
even רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda agrees that here order matters as well.
So you read the words צורך פנים, tzorech panim, the necessity of
the
innermost—things that are done, right, things that are done for the sake
of
inside. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנן Tnan now let's see if
let's see if this is going to work that רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda will say that order matters there as well.
אם עד שלא גמר מתנות שבפנים נשפך הדם יביא דם אחר ויחזור
ויחל בתחילה מבפנים. Im ad shelo gamar matnos shebifnim nishpach hadam yavi
dam acher veyachzor veyachel betchila mibifnim. So the משנה Mishna says that
the סיפא seifa the second part of the משנה Mishna doesn't talk
about order but talks about what happens if the blood spilled and
you have to pick it up. Do you pick it up where
you left off or from the beginning of that section? So it
says if you're not done yet in the קודש הקודשים Kodesh Hakodashim
and you spilled the blood you have to go and bring new
blood. Now how do you bring new blood? What do you have
to do to get new blood? You have to שחט shecht it
again. So look at what happens. You did this whole thing right
you did the whole order you know you did the חפינה chapina
you did the קטורת ketores right you got the blood of the
פר par now here you are getting the blood of you did
the blood of the פר par you're at number four doing the
blood of the פר par and then it spills. So it says
uh-oh it spilled in the middle you got to get you got
to get new blood of the פר. par. What do you have
to do now again? What do you have to do? שחיטת הפר.
Shechitas hapar. If you're going all the way back to number one
of the שחיטת הפר shechitas hapar then it's not just enough to
שחט shecht the פר par and go bring in the blood. If
you have to start again at שחיטת הפר shechitas hapar you got
to do again I'm not sure about the הגרלה hagrala we could
talk about that but you certainly got to do the קטורת ketores
next right? And if you got to do the חפינה chapina then
you have to bring the קטורת ketores next. So how is it
that you could just say oh just שחט shecht the פר? par?
What do you mean just שחט shecht the פר? par? As soon
as you go back to שחט shecht the פר par you got
to do if רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda didn't care about עבודה avoda
didn't say the order didn't matter out here there's no problem this
could be רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. Fine go שחט shecht the פר
par we don't care about there we only care right here right
it would be fine. But once רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda cares about
this as well and everybody cares about this as soon as you
go back to שחיטת הפר shechitas hapar you have to go bring
the קטורת. ketores. How did the משנה Mishna not mention that?
Okay so ויחזור ויחל בתחילה מבפנים veyachzor veyachel betchila mibifnim says go
get more blood. ואי איתא Ve-i issa if it's true that even
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda demands the order of the stuff that's done
out there that's done by the שחיטה shechita and the חפינה chapina
יחזור ויחפוץ מיבעי ליה. yachzor veyachpoz mibai lei. It shouldn't just say
get more blood it should say go back שחט shecht do another
חפינה chapina not only another חפינה chapina go bring the קטורת ketores
again and then do the blood. It's a lot you got to
do. So the גמרא Gemara says okay so that's the גמרא's Gemara
answer. בקטורת לא קמיירי Bektoret lo kamairi yeah we're not talking about
the קטורת. ketores. Yeah you get the blood and then you do
everything else that you got to you need to do in the
middle as well. But אין הכי נמי ein hachi nami look at
רש"י Rashi ומיהו ודאי צריך להקטיר קטורת אחרת אחר שחיטת פר זה.
umihu vadai tzarich lehaktir ketoret acheret achar shechitas par ze. Okay
so although the משנה Mishna just says get more blood what it
means by get more blood is שחט shecht it do the חפינה
chapina do the קטורת ketores it's a lot it's a lot to
do.
I know I know but that's the גמרא's Gemara challenge. Okay now
we're going to have a very similar statement by עולא Ulla with
a similar challenge. אמר עולא Amar Ulla so says עולא Ulla שעיר
seir yeah that would
mean that the לא מעכב lo meakev really has not done everything
well as opposed
to just that one act that he's taken out of order he
really has
well once you need to no just doing one act out of
order just means that that act didn't count but once you need
to go back up this is not just because he did something
out of order this is because it spilled and you had to
go higher up into process and here the higher then you got
to keep the order.
Okay אמר עולא Amar Ulla שעיר ששחטו קודם מתן דמו של פר
לא עשה ולא כלום seir sheshachato kodem matan damo shel par lo
asa velo klum let's say you
שחטed shecht the שעיר seir before you did the blood of the
פר par לא עשה ולא כלום lo asa velo klum and presumably
this means even according to רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. So it's the
same idea okay if you did right the שעיר seir before you
did the blood of the פר par right although this is something
that is done outside not it's also true that you go by
this and by that but anyway he's saying the same thing that
if you did this before you finished the פר par the שחיטה
shechita of the שעיר seir was no good. Okay so that's also
giving now you know here half of the idea is what's in
here and half is what's out here you use something out here
to interrupt something that was in here but now we're claiming it
doesn't matter anyway that according to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda all of
this order matters. So it's a similar statement in that line that
order matters even by that stuff that's done for the sake of
the inside. So now let's see about the implications. תנן Tnan so
now is this going to really work? תנן הקדים דמה של שעיר
לדם הפר יחזור ויזה מדם השעיר אחר דם הפר Tnan hikdim damah
shel seir ledam hapar yachzor veyaze midam haseir achar dam hapar right
the משנה Mishna says and this is the משנה Mishna when it
was talking about the order if you did the blood of the
שעיר seir before the blood of the פר par יחזור ויזה מדם
השעיר אחר דם הפר yachzor veyaze midam haseir achar dam hapar fine
the blood of the שעיר seir didn't count do it later. Okay
so meaning the משנה Mishna said that you're in here and you
jumped and you did the דם השעיר dam haseir before the דם
הפר dam hapar you jumped and you did 5b before the דם
הפר dam hapar it says all right fine so go do your
דם הפר dam hapar and then you do some of your שעיר
seir afterwards. The only point is that it forgot something before because
in order to get the blood of the שעיר seir right what
did you do you had to שחט shecht the שעיר seir but
the שחיטה shechita of the שעיר... seir... the שחיטה shechting of the
שעיר seir comes before, right, comes after the blood of the פר.
par. So you basically have in order if you did the דם
השעיר dam haseir up here, it means you שחט shchted the שעיר
seir before you did the דם הפר. dam hapar. So it shouldn't
just say just say hold on to the blood and do it
after the פר. par. It should say do the פר par and
then שחט shcht another שעיר. seir. Okay? Same type of a question.
If you שחט shcht the שעיר seir you
have to do another הגרלה? hagrala? Yeah we're going to get to
that. We'll get to that. ואם איתא יחזור וישחוט מבעי ליה. Ve'im
isah yachzor veyishchot miba'ei leih. Should say go שחט. shcht. You can't
say oh we're not talking about the blood of the שעיר seir
like you said before, we're not talking about the קטורת. ketoret. We
are talking about the blood of the שעיר. seir. So how can
it just say you do the blood of the שעיר seir after?
It should say you gotta שחט shcht after and then do the
blood of the שעיר. seir. So תרגמה עולא במתנות שבהיכל. Targuma Ulla
bematanot shebeheichal. No, when the משנה mishna said that you did the
blood of שעיר seir early, it's not talking about the קודש קדשים.
Kodesh Kodashim. It's talking about the היכל. Heichal. וכן אמר רב אפיס
במתנות שבהיכל. Vechein amar Rav Afis bematanot shebeheichal.
What it's saying is if you did seven before six. Everything is
שחט. shchted. That's all done. And then you got a שעיר seir
and you did the שעיר seir before the פר, par, then just
hold off, do the פר par and then do the שעיר seir
again afterwards. That's easy. But here, if you did the שעיר seir
before the פר, par, then it also means you שחט shchted the
שעיר seir before the פר. par. Then do the פר, par, שחט
shcht another שעיר seir and do it after. So by now saying
that everybody agrees on the stuff out here, we're making the idea
of oh just pick up, you know, when when you know if
you got interrupted just get some more just שחט shcht another thing
get some more blood or oh just wait and do it the
right order a lot more complicated. Because as soon as you have
to go back to doing something here, you gotta do out everything
כסדר. ke'seder. Okay? And that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying.
First in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim is the כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. Yeah. Yeah, you gotta trust his reporting about what happened.
Okay.
Anybody else in the היכל? Heichal?
No. I mean, anybody else in the היכל? Heichal? Who's mixing the
blood? No, כל אדם kol adam the גמרא Gemara says it includes
בהיכל. beHeichal. No no no he's מפרש mefaresh on the steps. The
גמרא Gemara says the וכל אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד vechol adam
lo yihyeh beohel moed is the whole היכל. Heichal. Who told us
that?
Did we even
discuss the אולם, ulam, whether that was included?
Wait, what'd you say about this?
No, I know it's a funny yeah. Okay. וכן בהיכל וכן במזבח.
Vechein beHeichal vechein bamizbe'ach. Now, now so that's the ביאור be'eir of
the order. Now we get onto this issue about what about
bracketing the order issue as we said. If you get interrupted,
you know,
if you're in the middle of the הזיות hazayot here, you gotta
get new דם dam and you gotta according to the first opinion
start again from the beginning like you were at one and three
but it spilled. So get new דם dam and start again from
the one, right? And that's what we said here. But then let's
say you did this and you got out here and you got
interrupted here. Then it spilled here. Then just have to restart here.
You don't have to restart all the way
there, right? So this is a unit by itself, this is a
unit by itself, this is a unit by itself. If any of
them the דם dam spills and you have to begin again, if
you finished the previous unit you don't have to go back to
the previous unit. You only have to begin again the unit you
were in.
Okay that was the point of the no more דם dam left
because it
also no then you have to שחט. shcht. Yeah yeah yeah but
we're ignoring the שחט shechting and the order problem. Whatever the issue
is with the שחט shechting in the order anyway it becomes becomes
moot after you've done with this but if it spills then you
don't have to go back and say oh the whole thing got
interrupted go back to the beginning. Just go back to the beginning
of each unit. If it spilled during this unit, go back to
I mean this was the פר, par, you know, whatever. This unit,
this unit, this unit. Just go back to that beginning. Okay?
So וכן, vechein, okay so that's what it says.
וכן בהיכל וכן במזבח. Vechein beHeichal vechein bamizbe'ach. תנו רבנן. Tano rabbanan.
וכיפר... Vekipper... now
before we get to this issue of the כפרה kapparah being separate
for each location and going back to the beginning of the unit,
we first talk about the פסוקים p'sukim about what it's supposed to
be. And this becomes very important and significant in terms of the
whole meaning of the עבודה. avoda. Now it says in the פסוקים
p'sukim in אחרי מות Acharei Mot it says the following. It says,
it says a lot of times that you are atoning for the
קודש. Kodesh. Okay, but I want to just read to you it
says, okay so first
it says when you're done with the with the וכיפר על הקודש
מטומאות בני ישראל ומפשעיהם לכל חטאתם. vechipper al hakodesh mitumot b'nei yisrael
umipisheihem l'chol chatotam.
That's what it says after you did the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
וכן יעשה לאהל מועד השוכן אתם בתוך טומאתם Vechein ya'aseh l'ohel moed
hashochen itam b'toch tumotam which is the פרוכת. parochet. Okay? And then
it says again ויצא אל המזבח וכיפר עליו veyatza el hamizbe'ach vechipper
alav etc.
וכילה מכפר את הקודש vechila mikaper et hakodesh that we read yesterday,
ואת אהל מועד ואת המזבח. ve'et ohel moed ve'et hamizbe'ach. Okay? And
etc. וסמך אהרן שתי ידיו... vesamach aharon shei yadav... so then you
do the whole thing with the sending the שעיר לעזאזל. seir la'azazel.
And then
it says towards the very end וכיפר את מקדש
הקודש,
vechipper et mikdash
hakodesh, so it's the very end of the whole אחרי מות Acharei
Mot section of the עבודה. avoda. It says וכיפר ve-chipper את...
all the עבודה avodah is done. וכיפר את מקדש הקודש, vechipper et
mikdash hakodesh, which is presumably קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, ואת אהל מועד
ואת המזבח יכפר. ve'et ohel moed ve'et hamizbe'ach yechaper. So again the
presumed פרוכת parochet and now the altar. You're saying אהל מועד ohel
moed
is the פרוכת parochet itself? What? You're saying אהל מועד ohel moed
is the פרוכת parochet itself?
Well that's what the גמרא Gemara says before.
Because if it says ואת אהל מועד ve'et ohel moed it must
mean...
as opposed to being taken as like unit. Well the גמרא Gemara
says when the פסוק pasuk said before after he's done with the
כפרה kaparah it says וכן יעשה לאהל מועד ve-chen ya-aseh le-ohel moed
that the way he does the atonement on אהל מועד ohel moed
is the דם dam of the of the פרוכת. paroches. וכיפר את
מקדש הקודש ואת אהל מועד ואת המזבח יכפר ועל הכהנים ועל כל
עם הקהל יכפר. ve-chipper es mikdash ha-kodesh ve-es ohel moed ve-es ha-mizbe'ach
yechapper ve-al ha-kohanim ve-al kol am ha-kahal yechapper. Okay,
so let's see how the גמרא Gemara interprets this. וכיפר so this
is at the very end. וכיפר את מקדש הקודש ve-chipper es mikdash
ha-kodesh זה לפני ולפנים. zeh lifnai velifnim. Okay, that's the קודש קדשים.
kodesh kodashim. אהל מועד ohel moed זה היכל. zeh heichal. Because again,
this again as I just said to Michael, when it said before
after he's done with the קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim וכן יעשה לאהל
מועד ve-chen ya-aseh le-ohel moed
was the interpretation of the blood on the פרוכת. paroches. So fine,
that's the היכל. heichal. אהל מועד ohel moed is the היכל heichal
and the עבודה avodah he does on the פרוכת. paroches. מזבח mizbe'ach
כמשמעו. kemashma'o.
The עבודה avodah he does on the on the golden altar, the
דם. dam. יכפר yechapper אלו עזרות. elu azaros.
So now that only gets you everything in the היכל. heichal. So
יכפר yechapper includes the עזרה, azarah, the outside of the of the
היכל, heichal, the open-air space where the מזבח mizbe'ach is. הכהנים ha-kohanim
כמשמעו. kemashma'o.
So it atones for the כהנים. kohanim. עם הקהל am ha-kahal אלו
ישראל. elu Yisrael. That's the ציבור. tzibbur. יכפר, yechapper, the extra יכפר
yechapper אלו הלווים elu ha-Leviyim gets you לווים. Leviyim. It's interesting that
they're not included in עם הקהל am ha-kahal once you I guess
separate out the כהנים, kohanim, you have to assume that the לווים
Leviyim also would deserve separate treatment.
So עם הקהל am ha-kahal here includes men and women? Presumably.
Okay, well let's not get there right now, but yes. Okay, so
that's what you have in the end פסוק. pasuk. Now the פשט
pshat of the פסוקים psukim actually and this is important because the
פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is really focusing on the two
separate aspects of what the עבודה avodah of יום כיפור Yom Kippur
is about. Because the עבודה avodah. of יום כיפור Yom Kippur as
we've been discussing a lot in the פשט pshat of the פסוקים
psukim is all about וכיפר את הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל ומפשעיהם לכל
חטאתם וכן יעשה לאהל מועד השוכן איתם ve-chipper es ha-kodesh mi-tum'os bnei
Yisrael u-mipisheihem le-chol chatosam ve-chen ya-aseh le-ohel moed ha-shochen itam as it's
about purifying, not atoning, but purifying the temple so that God can
continue to dwell in the temple, cleansing it from the sin that
somehow has clogged it up. That's the basic עבודה. avodah But then
what you get is you get the שעיר לעזאזל se'ir la-azazel and
the שעיר לעזאזל se'ir la-azazel what does that function? That says that
the שעיר se'ir what does that do? It says והתוודה עליו את
כל עוונות בני ישראל ואת כל פשעיהם לכל חטאתם, ve-hisvaddah alav es
kol avonos bnei Yisrael ve-es kol pisheihem le-chol chatosam, right? So that
and it's sending away the עוונות avonos of בני ישראל. bnei Yisrael.
So there presumably the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk presumably is
that the first part has to do with the cleansing of the
מקדש mikdash and then it says ועל הכהנים ועל כל עם הקהל
יכפר ve-al ha-kohanim ve-al kol am ha-kahal yechapper is presumably at least
עם הקהל am ha-kahal is the שעיר לעזאזל. se'ir la-azazel. The interesting
question to ask is what does it mean על הכהנים? al ha-kohanim?
Are the כהנים kohanim included in the שעיר לעזאזל se'ir la-azazel and
there sort of that atones for their sins or are the כהנים
kohanim included in somehow the thing of going on what's going on
in the מקדש? mikdash? Now if you think about now now the
תורה Torah here singled them out separately which indicates that there's some
distinct status here. Now it does say by אהרן Aharon וכיפר בעדו
ובעד
ביתו, ve-chipper ba'ado u-ve'ad beiso, right, also ובעד כל קהל ישראל. u-ve'ad
kol kehal Yisrael. Okay, so the question is and חז"ל Chazal understand
ובעד ביתו u-ve'ad beiso is not only his immediate household but the
כהנים. kohanim. So I would suggest that a simple understanding of the
פסוקים psukim is that the כהנים kohanim here are being atoned for,
yes, but not for their independent sins, not for their like personal
עבירות aveiros and their and their own sort of personal standing before
God, but they are being cleansed the way the מקדש mikdash is
being cleansed. You have to cleanse the מקדש mikdash so the same
way when the מקדש mikdash was initiated, right, there's the whole process
of חנוכת המשכן chanukas ha-mishkan המשכן ha-mishkan and so on and the
whole seven day period was a ritual with blood and whatever and
sanctifying and cleansing the מקדש mikdash and doing the same to the
כהנים. kohanim. This is a cleansing process which similarly cleanses the מקדש,
mikdash, cleanses the כהנים. kohanim. And therefore the ישראל, Yisrael, it's more
about their sins, they're not the ones being cleansed but they're the
ones who is more atoning for their sins. So therefore the and
if you think about it, the blood that's done in here when
he does the שחיטת הפר shechitas ha-par and the וידוי viduy on
the פר. par. Right? Remember the וידוי וכיפר בעדו ובעד ביתו. viduy
ve-chipper ba'ado u-ve'ad beiso.
ושחיטת השעיר ve-shechitas ha-se'ir does not have a וידוי. viduy. So therefore
this, right, which relates to the כהנים kohanim and all of this,
this is cleansing the מקדש mikdash but it comes with the וידוי
viduy which is for him and his household, presumably the כהנים. kohanim.
So it's cleansing the מקדש mikdash and cleansing the כהנים. kohanim. Okay.
So the שעיר לעזאזל se'ir la-azazel which has the וידוי viduy is
being מכפר mechapper for בני ישראל. bnei Yisrael. So that's how I
would suggest is the פשט הפסוקים pshat ha-psukim about what is going
on. Okay. The one question to ask is what's the שעיר se'ir
doing in here? That שעיר se'ir separate from the פר. par. The
שעיר לעזאזל se'ir la-azazel is for the sins of בני ישראל. bnei
Yisrael.
So what you're saying, are you saying to say that
the מקדש mikdash and by extension the כהנים, kohanim, עם כהן גדול,
im Kohen Gadol, are just cleansed of these
ritual infractions like oh like I did a blood one or is
it really their that the מקדש Mikdash is cleansed from the טומאות
Tumot from all sorts of things including in other words let's say
a כהן Kohen murders somebody is that only on יום כיפור? Yom
Kippur? Or is it just... No no no this is the whole
point the כהנים Kohanim are the incarnated מקדש Mikdash so what's done
to them is a parallel to what needs to be done to
the physical structure.
We're not talking about the whole difference and this is how it's
going to be contrasted to the approach that the גמרא Gemara takes
is our current way of thinking about it which is very much
sin you know as a personal as you know my personal sin
and my sin before God and my having to atone and cleanse
myself sort of for my sin meaning to make myself a better
as a person and to make and to free me from the
punishment that it's deserving and all of that. But in the תורה
Torah the idea of cleansing the מקדש Mikdash is whenever anybody sins
I don't care if it's the כהנים Kohanim I don't care if
it's about טומאה Tumah I don't care if it's about לשון הרע
Lashon Hara whenever anybody sins that sin pollutes and in a way
drives away or has the potential of driving away God's presence and
the pollution adheres like sticks to the walls it's soot that sticks
to the walls of the מקדש Mikdash whenever sin is done. The
same way the sin pollutes the land ולא תטמאו את הארץ Velo
Titamu Et Ha'aretz אשר Asher right? So your sin is מטמא Metameh
the ארץ Aretz and your sin is מטמא Metameh the מקדש Mikdash
and this holy place and therefore in order for God to continue
to dwell there needs to be a ritual cleansing of that metaphysical
effect of the sin. I don't care about you it's not about
you it's about the מקדש Mikdash and cleansing it from the sin
that was done in the past so God can continue to dwell
therein. So the כהנים Kohanim also have the function in the מקדש
Mikdash they're part of the כלי המקדש Klei HaMikdash so they're also
in a way polluted I would argue and have to be cleansed
the same way when the מקדש Mikdash was sanctified it was the
מקדש Mikdash and the כהנים Kohanim that were sanctified by an initial
by a similar process. So that I would say is all of
the
מקדש הקודש Mikdash HaKodesh and that's part of the וידוי Viduy הפר
HaPar דעצמו ובעד ביתו D'atzmo U'va'ad Beito and the פר Par is
what's doing all of this whereas ועל כל עם הקהל יכפר V'al
Kol Am HaKahal Yichaper we're no longer talking about this you know
about this sort of cleansing of God dwelling we're talking maybe closer
to an idea of you know you're spared your sins and that
is the שעיר לעזאזל Se'ir La'azazel which takes because by the שעיר
לעזאזל Se'ir La'azazel it says right והתודה עליו את כל עונות בני
ישראל ואת כל פשעיהם לכל חטאתם V'hitvada Alav Et Kol Avonot Bnei
Yisrael V'et Kol Pish'eihem L'kol Chatotam okay.
So that's anyway why the שעיר Se'ir in here what?
So that's a good question what exactly is the שעיר Se'ir there
doing which doesn't have a וידוי. Viduy. Anyway that's what I would
say is the פשט Pshat let's see let's just see what the
גמרא Gemara says yes.
So that would be it right so the personal sins of the
כהנים Kohanim might go with the שעיר Se'ir according to that it's
a little bit unclear what where the personal sins of the כהנים
Kohanim are included and it's also a little bit unclear what the
שעיר Se'ir in here is doing but anyway that's what I would
say is like roughly the פשט. Pshat. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does with it. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says so it
says הושוו כולם לכפרה אחת Hushvu Kulam Lekappara Achat so they're all
equated in one כפרה Kappara why are they all equated in one
כפרה Kappara because it says the last יכפר Yichaper says ועל ועל
ועל כל עם הקהל יכפר V'al V'al V'al Kol Am HaKahal Yichaper
so the ועל הכהנים ועל כל עם הקהל יכפר V'al HaKohanim V'al
Kol Am HaKahal Yichaper so that sort of wraps it all together
so הושוו כולם לכפרה אחת. Hushvu Kulam Lekappara Achat. So כולי מתכפרי
בשעיר המשתלח בשאר עבירות Kulei Mitkapri B'se'ir HaMishtaleach B'sh'ar Averot דברי רבי
יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says is that
since it says a יכפר Yichaper at the end על כל עם
הקהל על הכהנים ועל כל עם הקהל יכפר Al Kol Am HaKahal
Al HaKohanim V'al Kol Am HaKahal Yichaper means there's one כפרה Kappara
that works equally for the כהנים Kohanim and ישראל Yisrael well it's
not this פר Par and שעיר Se'ir that's distinct so it must
be that the one thing the שעיר לעזאזל Se'ir La'azazel is the
one thing that works for both of them that's what רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says okay and that atones for all of their personal
sins
even though they already had some of it taken care of.
Well he might not say that well the key is the word
בשאר עבירות B'sh'ar Averot and now what you have to know is
as opposed to what I just laid out to you as what
I would say פשט הפסוקים Pshat HaPsukim חז"ל Chazal understand it very
differently because they understand they've moved away from this understanding of this
like metaphysical טומאה Tumah in the מקדש Mikdash that has to be
cleansed and they're thinking very much about the עבירות Averot that have
to be atoned for it's about your sin as a personal person
your sins that adheres to you that you have to be atoned
for. So they have they they
have interpreted the whole sense of being מכפר את מקדש הקודש Mechaper
Et Mikdash HaKodesh not to cleanse the מקדש Mikdash but you know
what they say it means? It means to atone for you for
your sin if you entered in the מקדש Mikdash when you were
טמא. Tameh. So all of this huge ritual here is about any
person that has entered the מקדש Mikdash when they are טמא Tameh
this will be atoned for that sin. Now even that is more
limited because if I enter the מקדש Mikdash when I was טמא
Tameh I bring a special קרבן Korban it's called a קרבן עולה
ויורד Korban Oleh VeYored why do I need this to atone for
me? So if you look at רש"י Rashi for example look at
רש"י Rashi right רש"י Rashi says זה בפנים ולפנים Zeh Bifnim Velifnim
okay you see the first narrow line he says כיפר בדמים הללו
על טומאה ש Kipper Bedamim Halalu Al Tumah She... כי בדמים הללו
על טומאה שאירעה לפני ולפנים אם נכנס אדם שם בטומאה ואין בה
ידיעה בסוף. ki badamim halalu al tumah sheira'ah lifnai v'lifnim im nichnas
adam sham b'tumah v'ein bah yedi'ah basof. Only if I entered there
when I was טמא tamei and I didn't know at the end,
but had there been ידיעה בתחילה, yedi'ah bit'chilah, but I knew at
the beginning I was טמא, tamei, then I forgot and then I
never realized at the end. ואילפינן מקרא בפרק קמא דשבועות v'alfinan mikra
b'perek kama d'shavuot שזהו תולה לה להגן מן היסורין shezehu toleh lah
lahagen min hayisurin that this protects me from punishment עד שיודע לו
ויביא בעולה ויורד. ad sheyivada lo v'yavi b'olah v'yored. But when I
become aware that I sinned, then I bring a normal קרבן. korban.
So all of this huge ritual of יום כיפור Yom Kippur is
done temporarily for the few individuals that entered in the מקדש Mikdash
when they were טמא, tamei, knew at the beginning, forgot, didn't realize
at the end, and it's done to protect them from the sin
until they become aware that they sinned and then they can bring
their own קרבן. korban. Okay, that's what all this is for. Like
why do we do the huge thing on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
just for that? It's very difficult to understand. But what it shows
you is the shift from this more metaphysical, national, you know, God's
presence sense, to the personal עבירה aveirah emphasis of חז"ל. Chazal. So
according to that, one minute, all of this is done for, all
of this is done for טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tumath mikdash v'kodashav, right,
this is done for the sin of טומאת מקדש, tumath mikdash, the
literal טומאת מקדש, tumath mikdash, right, the sin of טומאת מקדש, tumath
mikdash, not the metaphysical, the individual sins, alright, in the individual sins
of טומאת מקדש. tumath mikdash. That's what
שעיר המשתלח Sa'ir Ha-Mishtaleach is, notice the phrase used by the שעיר
המשתלח. Sa'ir Ha-Mishtaleach. It says שאר עבירות. shear aveirot. שאר עבירות, shear
aveirot, right? So this takes care of two out of, one out
of 613 sins, okay? And only under very special circumstances. And this
takes care of the other 612, both for the כהנים Kohanim and
for ישראל. Yisrael. And this is for separately. Now that becomes a
little bizarre as I said and you have to assume that even
when they talk about your individual sin of טומאת מקדש tumath mikdash
presumably somehow that has some larger effect on the מקדש. Mikdash. Or
else it's very very hard to understand why all this is being
done just for that.
Well, to use a paradigm that you have introduced often. Yes.
A post-חורבן churban theology
narrows the significance of the מקדש Mikdash because they needed theologically not
to be so dependent.
I understand. I totally get why after right, after the חורבן, churban,
right. No you're right, I've been saying it implicitly but you're right,
after the חורבן, churban, you know, the, you have to shift the
idea of personal sin and personal responsibility and move away from that
whole, you know, from that whole focus and the importance that that
had. I totally agree but it merely minimizes that role. Okay, now
by the way here's the other point that רש"י Rashi indicated that
you might not have noticed. When we say וכיפר את מקדש הקודש
ואת אהל מועד ואת המזבח. ve-chiper et mikdash ha-kodesh ve-et ohel moed
ve-et ha-mizbe'ach.
I said פשטות peshtut is it's cleansing these places. You do a
ritual in here, it cleanses here. Ritual out here, it cleanses here.
Ritual here, it cleanses here. But according to רש"י, Rashi, you know
what it's doing? It's not cleansing those places. In here it's atoning
for the sin if you were טמא tamei when you entered in
the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. In here it's atoning for the sin
if you were טמא tamei when you were in the היכל. Heichal.
And over here it's doing the sin if you were טמא tamei
when you were up by the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So it's just atoning
for a sin that took place in a different place and it's
not a cleansing of the whole place, it's atoning for a different
sin. Of course the question is like how did you sin in
here without already sinning getting טמא tamei in here? Like maybe you
became טמא tamei when you were in here. Why do you need
a special atonement for being טמא tamei by the מזבח? mizbe'ach? I
mean you're just טמא tamei in the היכל. Heichal. But as well
it would be that you did an עבודה avoda, by the מזבח
mizbe'ach but you didn't spend a long enough time in the היכל
Heichal in order for that to have been a problem. So it
all becomes just different situations of the sin of טומאה tumah that
it's atoning for. And very much stops being a cleansing of the
place to atoning for a particular type of a sin that you
have done.
And that's only with כהנים?
Kohanim? No. The פר par is for the כהנים Kohanim and the
שעיר sa'ir is for the ישראל. Yisrael. How ישראל Yisrael got in
here to do a טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumath mikdash v'kodashav I'd like
to know. But correct.
But then how do you do the שאר עבירות? shear aveirot? Because
you also mentioned you did the שאר עבירות, shear aveirot, you did
nothing specific for the שאר עבירות. shear aveirot.
Yeah, so somehow right, I don't know, somehow it affects that כפרה
kaparah without doing a particular. Or maybe it would be the שיירים
shirayim that we say שיירים מעכבין. shirayim me'akvin. I don't know. Okay,
so that's anyway that's what ר' יהודה Rebbi Yehudah says. The שעיר
המשתלח Sa'ir Ha-Mishtaleach is all the other עבירות aveirot and the פר
ושעיר par v'sa'ir even for the כהנים Kohanim because they have an
equation. ר' שמעון Rebbi Shimon אומר omer no. כשם שדם השעיר הנעשה
בפנים מכפר על ישראל בטומאת מקדש וקדשיו, keshem she-dam ha-sa'ir ha-na'asah bifnim
mechaper al Yisrael be-tumath mikdash v'kodashav,
the same way the blood of the שעיר sa'ir atones for the
sin of being מטמא מקדש וקדשיו metamei mikdash v'kodashav for ישראל. Yisrael.
כך דם הפר מכפר על הכהנים בטומאת מקדש וקדשיו. kach dam ha-par
mechaper al ha-kohanim be-tumath mikdash v'kodashav.
Same by the blood of the פר, par, that's the parallel. Okay,
but you have an, you have a lack of parallel because you
did a וידוי viduy on the פר par that you did not
do on the שעיר. sa'ir. So וכשם שוידוי של שעיר המשתלח מכפר
על ישראל. u-keshem she-viduy shel sa'ir ha-mishtale'ach mechaper al Yisrael.
So that works for the, the וידוי viduy works for the other
sins. So the וידוי viduy on the שעיר המשתלח Sa'ir Ha-Mishtaleach works
for ישראל. Yisrael. בשאר עבירות, beshear aveirot, the other 612, כך וידוי
של פר מכפר לכהנים בשאר עבירות. kach viduy shel par mechaper lakohanim
beshear aveirot. Okay? So he says, I don't agree. I don't think
the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtaleach works for ישראל Yisrael and כהנים Kohanim
together. I think that there's an equation of how they function, so
the דם dam equally does the sin of טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. tumat
mikdash vekodashav. The וידוי viduy works for the other 612 and the
וידוי viduy on the שעיר se'ir works for ישראל. Yisrael. So this
works for the כהנים Kohanim for the 612 and the וידוי viduy
of the שעיר se'ir works for ישראל. Yisrael. So according to רבי
נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemya, excuse me, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, I think it's
fascinating in two ways. Way number one is that even when it
comes to the personal sin and not just מקדש וקדשיו mikdash vekodashav
where you would understand why to single out כהנים, Kohanim, but even
when it comes to the other 612 and the personal sins, there's
going to be a different ritual to atone for כהנים Kohanim than
there is for ישראל. Yisrael. So I think that that's like in
itself a fascinating question, why would they get a different ritual of
atonement for their personal sins than the rest of ישראל? Yisrael? Because
they were doing עבודה, avoda.
so it has to- I
understand, but that gets to the other issue about this sense of
sin being מטמא, metame, which I think the גמרא Gemara is moving
away from here. So if you think about it in much less
than that sense and just as the personal atonement, maybe they have
to be especially cleansed because they're representing ישראל Yisrael to God, they
have to do even a higher level of atonement or something. But
anyway, that's important point number one, that even in general sins, they
have a separate atonement. But important point number two is, notice again
the radical nature of the shift. No longer is the דם dam
being מכפר. mechaper. What's doing most of the כפרה? kapara? The וידוי.
viduy. The very act of וידוי. viduy. And if you talk about
a transition from a מקדש mikdash type of ritual where the ritual
cleanses to a non-מקדש mikdash personal sin, guilt, responsibility, transformation,
וידוי, viduy, תשובה, teshuva, we have now completely shifted the weight of
everything that's happening here. We have said all of this is all
about the ritual, but you know what really is doing the atonement
here? That act of וידוי. viduy. That act of וידוי viduy covers
for on the פר par did all the other atonements for all
for all the other 612, the וידוי viduy of the- not the
sending of the שעיר לעזאזל, se'ir l'azazel, the וידוי viduy on the
שעיר se'ir is what achieved the atonement. So that's that complete shift
of emphasis which ultimately gets you past מקדש mikdash into a post-מקדש
mikdash reality. What do you mean what's the point of sending? How-
sending it? I don't know, okay anyway, maybe בתנאי bitnai that it
was sent, but still the emphasis is on the וידוי, viduy, not
on the ritual.
So the דם dam is just for טומאה tuma and
the וידוי viduy is for everything else. The דם dam is just
for the טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumat mikdash vekodashav and the וידוי viduy
covers everything else. So you really see the shift from the מקדש
mikdash to what's transitioning us to a post-מקדש mikdash reality by the
way what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is doing.
And okay, did you have a point on נושא nosei also, right?
What? That it- a
נושא עוון nosei avon versus kind of look at that all together.
Let's not worry about that. Okay anyway, so let's go on. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, so that
was very important and fascinating in terms of how we- what- what's
all this doing? We've been talking all about the details, what's it
all doing? And- and again, פשט הפסוקים pshat hapsukim I would argue
is it's doing a ritual cleansing at a national level for allowing
the שכינה Shechina to dwell and there's also the question of personal.
Even there you could distinguish the כהנים Kohanim as a type of
a part of the מקדש mikdash being cleansed at this ritual way
as opposed to the שעיר se'ir which is for the sin, which
is more classical way. And as opposed to now what the גמרא
Gemara has done, which is made it all about personal sin and
sort of separated out one particular sin from the rest than number
one. And then in רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, even in other sins,
a distinction between כהנים Kohanim and ישראל Yisrael and for him really
that all the weight is being carried by the וידוי, viduy, a
pretty radical shift. Okay, so that was really important. תנו רבנן. Tanu
rabanan. Now we get back to business about the- about the interruption
of the עבודה.
avoda Did you remind us when did they live רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
They were תלמידי רבי עקיבא. talmidei Rabbi Akiva. They were one generation
before רבי יהודה הנשיא.
Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi. The middle of the
second century.
Yes, yes. Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, וכילה מכפר. vechila mikaper.
So this is an earlier פסוק, pasuk, it sounds like the previous
פסוק pasuk but it's an earlier פסוק. pasuk. את הקודש. et hakodesh.
He finishes the קודש. kodesh. זה לפני ולפנים. ze lifnai velifnim. That's
קודש קודשים. kodesh kodashim. אהל מועד, ohel moed, זה היכל. ze heichal.
So אהל מועד ohel moed זה היכל ze heichal as we know.
מזבח, mizbeach, כמשמעו. kemashmao. מלמד שכולם כפרה כפרה בפני עצמן. melamed shekulam
kapara kapara bifnei atzman. So this gets us to the point of
our משנה. mishna. Before it was talking more theological what the effect
is, this gets us to the point of our משנה mishna which
is each thing is identified separately. So each- so each- the עבודה
is seen as a separate unit and if you're done, you never
have to go back to that unit. מכאן אמרו, mikan amru, נתן
מקצת מתנות שבפנים ונשפך הדם, natan miktzat matanot shebifnim venishpach hadam, if
it spilled in the middle of the קודש קודשים, kodesh kodashim, יביא
דם אחר ויתחיל בתחילה במתנות שבפנים. yavi dam acher veyatchil betchila bematanot
shebifnim. You have to start beginning of that unit of the קודש
קודשים. kodesh kodashim. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Shimon
omrim, אינו מתחיל ממקום שפסק. and that's the debate; they say no,
you pick up where you left off. Not only are you allowed
to, you have to, you don't go back to the beginning. We'll
see what that's about in a minute. But first we're going to
focus on the idea that when you do go back according to
the תנא קמא, Tana Kamma, it's only to the beginning of the
unit. גמר מתנות שבפנים, gamar matanot shebifnim, you finished the קודש קודשים
Kodesh Kodashim ונשפך הדם, venishpach hadam, and it spilled before you began
the פרוכת, parochet, that's easy. יביא דם אחר ויתחיל בתחילה במתנות שבהיכל.
yavi dam acher veyatchil batechila bematanot shebaheichal. Fine, it spilled before you
even began, everybody agrees: get more blood
and שחט shecht another cow, whatever, and begin the פרוכת. parochet. נתן
מקצת מתנות שבהיכל, natan mikzat matanot shebaheichal, you began a little bit
in the היכל. heichal. Notice again the emphasis by the way on
the היכל, heichal, not the פרוכת, parochet, because the act done towards
the פרוכת parochet is as we've seen in the פסוקים pesukim for
the sake of the whole היכל. heichal. So you're doing the blood
for the sake of the היכל, heichal, in the היכל, heichal, and
you did a little and now it spilled. ונשפך הדם, venishpach hadam,
יביא דם אחר ויתחיל בתחילה בהיכל. yavi dam acher veyatchil batechila baheichal.
So begin again at the beginning of that unit. Don't go to
the beginning of the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, go to the beginning
of the היכל. heichal. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים אינו מתחיל אלא
ממקום שפסק. Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Shimon omrim einu matchil ela mimakom shepasak.
No, you pick up where you left off. So that's the unit
of the היכל, heichal, that's its own separate unit. גמר מתנות שבהיכל
ונשפך הדם. gamar matanot shebaheichal venishpach hadam. Now you're done with היכל
heichal and you haven't begun the מזבח mizbeach yet and it spilled,
that's a no-brainer. יביא דם אחר ויתחיל בתחילה במתנות המזבח. yavi dam
acher veyatchil batechila bematanot hamizbeach. Fine. So you finished one, you didn't
begin the other, get more blood, שחט shecht another cow, whatever it
is, and begin the מזבח. mizbeach. Let's say it spilled in the
middle of the מזבח. mizbeach. נתן מקצת מתנות שבמזבח ונשפך הדם. natan
mikzat matanot shebamizbeach venishpach hadam. It spilled in the middle of the
מזבח. mizbeach. יביא דם אחר ויתחיל בתחילה במתנות המזבח. yavi dam acher
veyatchil batechila bematanot hamizbeach. So that's its own unit, so you begin
at the beginning of that unit and you begin with the מזבח
mizbeach again.
המזבח הזהב, hamizbeach hazahav, right? We're over here, right? The little one.
The little, right. So each one is a separate unit. So if
you spilled, begin at the beginning of the unit, don't go back
to the previous unit. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים
ממקום שפסק הוא מתחיל. Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Shimon omrim mimakom shepasak hu
matchil. No, I'm sorry, you pick up where you left
off. גמר מתנות שבמזבח ונשפך הדם. gamar matanot shebamizbeach venishpach hadam. You
finished the
מזבח mizbeach and spilled before you did the pouring by the יסוד
yesod of the outer altar. In that case, דברי הכל לא מעכב.
divrei hakol lo meakev. Everybody agrees it is not מעכב, meakev, which
is as opposed to what we said yesterday where we mentioned the
position that the שיריים sheyaryim is מעכב meakev by יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. The one place that שיריים sheyaryim is, could be מעכב meakev
is by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. It is actually, that is a
debated point as we saw yesterday. And here everybody holds that the
spilling of the remnants, the pouring of the remnants is not מעכב.
meakev. So if it spilled on the floor before you did the
ritual pouring of the שיריים sheyaryim on the יסוד המזבח, yesod hamizbeach,
that's fine, you're done.
Just wondering, it's not מעכב? meakev?
Because it never is מעכב. meakev.
Okay, but part of the חוקה chuka of יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? Yeah, yeah, but it was but it but it was
the debate of how you read דכילה מכפר אם כילה כיפר אם
כיפר כילה. dechila mikaper im chila kiper im kiper chila. That was
yesterday's דף. daf. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. Now, so
now let's look, so the first point is by identifying the separate
units, it's said that if you have to start again, you only
start at the beginning of a unit. But now we want to
understand the debate of whether you start again at the beginning of
a unit or you start where you left off. So let's take
a look. אמר רבי יוחנן בשני מקרא אחד דורשין. Amar Rabbi Yochanan
bishnei mikra echad dorshin. They both in the debate of whether you
go to the beginning or you pick up where you left off
is all based on how you interpret a פסוק. pasuk. מדם חטאת
הכיפורים אחת
בשנה. midam chatat hakippurim achat bashana. It says from the blood of
the sin offering of the הכיפורים kippurim אחת בשנה achat bashana once
in a year you should do this to atone. So if you
remember before, the אחת achat has been used in other ways, not
just to mean once a year, but to mean one in other
ways. Okay, so let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara
does with it. רבי מאיר סבר חטאת אחת אמרתי לך ולא שתי
חטאות. Rabbi Meir savar chatat achat amarti lecha velo shtei chatatot. There
should only be one sin offering, not two. So therefore what happens
if you did one, two, three and it spilled and you had
to שחט shecht another animal and if you picked up where you
left off then in the מתנות matanot of the unit you're doing
you would be using blood of two separate animals. So he says
no, in any you can look at units individually, not one sin
offering for all three units. That's what we get the blessing by
looking at the units individually. You don't have to go back to
something you finished. But in every individual unit, it can only be
blood of one sacrifice. חטאת אחת אמרתי לך ולא שתי חטאות. chatat
achat amarti lecha velo shtei chatatot. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון סברי Rabbi
Eliezer veRabbi Shimon savri they hold, what do they when they say
no we don't let you go back to the beginning, you have
to continue where you left off, they hold differently. חיטוי אחד אמרתי
לך ולא שתי חיטויים. chitu echad amarti lecha velo shtei chituyim. One
process of sprinkling is what חטאת chatat can mean and not two
processes. Because if I did one, two, three and you told me
to start again or I did one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, then I've done two processes. I've done one halfway and then
I've done another the full way, right? So this is the choice
you have to make. Do you start over again so it's the
blood from the same animal for all seven? Or do you pick
up where you left off because to start over again would be
to be replicating, would be to be doing another process, an additional
process. Okay, so that's the debate. So it's not like they say
you're allowed
to pick
up. So each one says there has to be something unifying, either
one process or is it all from the blood of one animal?
Okay. תניא. Tanya. אמר
ליה אמר רבי, Amar lei amar Rabbi, said Rabbi, לי חילק רבי
יעקב בלוג. Li chilek Rabbi Yaakov balog. Okay? For me, Rabbi Yaakov
taught me, distinguished for me, differentiated for me when it comes to
the issue of the לוג. log. What does that mean? So of
course, as we all know, the לוג log refers to the לוג
שמן log shemen that is brought by a מצורע. metzora. Okay, and
when the מצורע, metzora, you have the purification process of the מצורע,
metzora, so it says that you take the blood of a, you
take, you take a לוג log of, of oil. A לוג log
is like a, like 12 ounces of oil. Okay, and you do
a ritual, you sprinkle the blood in the היכל. Heichal. The blood?
You sprinkle the oil in the היכל. Heichal. And then you put
the oil on his ear and on his thumb and on his
toe, and you pour it on his head. Okay, and you do
this whole process. What happens if in the middle of the process
it spills? Do you start the process again or do you pick
up where you left off? So Rabbi says, Rabbi Yaakov taught this
to me and he said, you know, when it comes to the
oil, everybody agrees. There's not a debate. It's different from the debate
by the blood. Why would everybody agree? So רש״י Rashi says, because
the פסוק pasuk says לוג אחד שמן. log echad shemen. It says
one לוג. log. So there, everybody would agree you need to use
the same לוג log for the whole process, so you have to
start from the beginning, you can't pick up in the middle. Here
we could discuss is it not to repeat the process or to
have the blood of the same cow, but of the same אשם.
asham. But there, he said everybody would agree, לוג אחד, log echad,
you have to use only one לוג log for the whole process,
so if it spills, start again from the beginning.
Because here it says חטאת. chatat.
You can't, you can't read it to say חיטוי. chittui. חטאת chatat
is ambiguous. It could be one sin offering or one process of
purification. But לוג אחד log echad does not mean one process, it
only means one לוג. log. So it has to be the same
לוג log for the whole process, so if it spills you have
to start
again.
It says מפורש אחד meforash echad here, but it could be חטאת
chatat could be interpreted two ways. Ah, חטאת chatat could be the
sin offering or the process. But לוג log means the one לוג
log of oil can only mean one thing, and therefore if it
spills you have to start again so it's the same לוג log
for the whole process. Okay? So let's take a
look. Okay, so לי חילק רבי יהודה רבי יעקב בלוג. Li chilek
Rabbi Yehuda Rabbi Yaakov balog. בלוג? Balog? Really? You're telling me that
it's different, they don't debate that? והתניא, Vehatanya, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan,
נתן מקצת מתנות שבפנים ונשפך הלוג. Natan miktzat matanot shebifnim venishpach halog.
So this is going to be a very quick ברייתא braita like
the previous one.
You did some of the sprinkling of the oil inside the, you
know, in the היכל Heichal and it spilled. יביא לוג אחר ויעשה
בתחילה במתנות שבהיכל. Yavi log acher veyaaseh betechila bematanot shebaheichal. Start again
the sprinkling of the oil from the beginning of the היכל. Heichal.
In the היכל Heichal you would sprinkle for seven times from the
לוג log of oil in the היכל. Heichal. That's what you do
for a מצורע. metzora. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים, Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi
Shimon omrim, ממקום שפסק הוא מתחיל. Mimakom shepasak hu matchil. But look,
they debate that as well. They say, no, don't go back to
the beginning, pick up where you left off. גמר מתנות שבהיכל ונשפך
הלוג. Gamar matanot shebaheichal venishpach halog.
Let's say you finished the sprinkling of the oil in the היכל
Heichal and it spilled before you began putting it on his ears
and thumb and toe. יביא לוג אחר ויתחיל בתחילה במתנות שבבהונות. Yavi
log acher veyatchil betechila bematanot shebabehonot.
So fine, if it spilled between those units, nobody disagrees, get more
oil and start when it and you know start putting it on
the thumb, the ears, and thumb. נתן מקצת מתנות שבבהונות. Natan miktzat
matanot shebabehonot.
Now let's say some of it spilled when you were did one
the thumb before you did the toe or something, ונשפך הלוג, venishpach
halog, יביא לוג אחר ויעשה בתחילה במתנות שבבהונות. yavi log acher veyaaseh
betechila bematanot shebabehonot.
So you start again that process with the, you know, with the
thumb and the toe. That's what you start beginning of the process.
רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Shimon, אומרים, ממקום שפסק הוא
מתחיל. mimakom shepasak hu matchil. No, pick up where you left off.
גמר מתנות שבבהונות ונשפך הלוג. Gamar matanot shebabehonot venishpach halog. And
let's say after you did the thumb and the toe it spilled,
and what you're supposed to do now is pour the rest of
the oil on the head. דברי הכל מתנת הראש אינה מעכבת. Divrei
hakol matnat harosh einah meakevet. Everybody says that that doesn't מעכב, meakev,
the same way spilling of the rest of the blood at the
base of the מזבח mizbeach isn't מעכב, meakev, the spilling of the
rest of the oil at the head of the מצורע metzora is
also not מעכב. meakev. So we'll get back to why the head
is different, but right now the point is you see it's the
same debate. The same way they debate by the blood, you start
at the beginning or pick up where you left off, here too
even though it says לוג אחד, log echad, they still say they
debate. Some say you need one לוג log for the whole thing
so you go to the beginning, and the other say רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer ורבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon you pick up where you left
off. So הגמרא hagemara says fine, אימא לי שנה רבי יעקב בלוג,
eima li shana Rabbi Yaakov balog, not לי חילק רבי יעקב בלוג.
li chilek Rabbi Yaakov balog. Not that Rabbi Yaakov told me it
was different by the case of the לוג, log, no, Rabbi Yaakov
taught me this debate by the case of the לוג. log. It's
the same by the case of the לוג. log. Okay, so now
the exact, so now we don't know where it gets from from
the פסוק pasuk because it's לוג אחד, log echad, how it's based
on the פסוק, pasuk, but nevertheless it's the same debate. There's do
you go to the beginning of a unit or do you pick
up where you left off? Now why is the head not מעכב,
meakev, the spilling of the oil on the head? So אמר מר,
amar mar, מתנת הראש אינה מעכבת, matnat harosh einah meakevet, the putting
on the head of the remnant of... So what's the פסוק? pasuk?
The פסוק pasuk says the following by the מצורע, metzora, it says
ולקח הכהן מלוג השמן ויצק על כף הכהן השמאלית וטבל הכהן אצבעו
הימנית מן השמן אשר על כפו השמאלית והזה מן השמן באצבעו
שבע פעמים לפני השם.
ve-lakach ha-kohen mi-log ha-shemen ve-yatzak al kaf ha-kohen ha-smalit ve-taval ha-kohen
etzba-o ha-yemanit min ha-shemen asher
al
kapo ha-smalit ve-hizah min ha-shemen
be-etzba-o sheva pe-amim lifnei Hashem.
So that's בפנים. bifnim. You take the oil and you sprinkle it
in the היכל. Heichal. ומיתר השמן אשר על כפו יתן הכהן על
תנוך אוזן המטהר הימנית ועל בהן ידו הימנית ועל בהן רגלו הימנית.
u-miyeter ha-shemen asher al kapo yiten ha-kohen al tnuch ozen ha-mitaher ha-yemanit
ve-al bohen yado ha-yemanit ve-al bohen raglo ha-yemanit. So you do the
ear, the thumb, and the toe. And then it says והנותר בשמן
אשר על כף הכהן יתן על ראש המטהר. ve-hanotar ba-shemen asher al
kaf ha-kohen yiten al rosh ha-mitaher.
You pour it on the top. Okay, so how do you know
the head isn't מעכב? me-akev? אילימא דכתיב והנותר מן השמן ilima de-chtiv
ve-hanotar min ha-shemen by the head. אלא מעתה ela me-ata והנותרת מן
המנחה ve-hanoteret min ha-minchah הכי נמי דלא מעכבי? hachi nami de-la me-akvei?
So it
says, it says a similar phrase, what's left over from the מנחה
minchah when after you take the, you know, the קמיצה. kmitzah. So
there too do we say it doesn't matter? Now the reality is
if you don't eat the remnants of the מנחה minchah you're still
יוצא. yotzei. But if the remnants of the מנחה minchah spills before
you offer up the קמיצה kmitzah it is invalid. So just because
it says נותר notar does not mean that it's not important. So
why do we say that the head doesn't matter? You could answer—the
גמרא Gemara says אלא ela no, here's why it's not important. שאני
התם דכתיב ומיתר והנותר. shani hatam de-chtiv u-miyeter ve-hanotar.
Here it's different because look what the פסוק pasuk says. When it
says to put it on the ear and the thumb, it says
ומיתר השמן אשר על כפו. u-miyeter ha-shemen asher al kapo.
Then after you're done with the ear and thumb it says והנותר
בשמן. ve-hanotar ba-shemen. So the נותר notar is what's left over from
what was already referred to as יתר השמן. yeter ha-shemen. So if
you look at רש"י, Rashi, look at רש"י Rashi he says מתנות
בהן matnot bohen he says like this: he says מתנות בהן קרויים
שיריים matnot bohen keruyim shiyrayim that's the last line of רש"י Rashi
דכתיב בהו ומיתר השמן. de-chtiv behu u-miyeter ha-shemen. So it says what's
the remnant, it talks when you put on the thumb. ומתנות הראש
קרויים שירי שיריים. u-matnot ha-rosh keruyim shirei shiyrayim.
That's the שירי שיריים, shirei shiyrayim, it's the leftovers of the leftovers.
דכתיב בהו והנותר בשיריים הראשונים יתן על ראש
המטהר. de-chtiv behu ve-hanotar ba-shiyrayim ha-rishonim yiten al rosh ha-mitaher. So what's
the leftovers of leftovers, that already is very
secondary and if you didn't do it it's not מעכב. me-akev. And
it's also fascinating to think, you know, pour what's left at the
base of the מזבח mizbe-ach by the blood, pour what's left on
the head of the מטהר. mitaher. To think about a very parallel
ritual. So the same way the pouring of the שיריים shiyrayim is
not מעכב me-akev even on יום כיפור Yom Kippur although with the
base, but that's how they hold everybody here, the pouring of the
ראש rosh of the מטהר mitaher is not מעכב. me-akev. Okay. אמר
רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan says רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: אשם מצורע
ששחטו שלא לשמו.
asham metzora she-shachato
she-lo lishmo. Now I am especially given the time not getting into
רש"י'ס Rashi's read of this גמרא. Gemara. תוספות Tosafot as תוספות Tosafot
has a very different גרסא girsa than רש"י. Rashi. It's not ששחטו
שלא לשמו, she-shachato she-lo lishmo,
it's the תוספות Tosafot גרסא girsa is if you look at the
first narrow line of תוספות, Tosafot, גרסת ר"ח אשם מצורע שנשפך דמו
קודם מתן בהונות. girsa d'Rach asham metzora she-nishpach damo kodem matan behonot.
Okay.
So basically a very parallel case. What the תורה Torah says by
the אשם asham of the מצורע, metzora, the first narrow line in
תוספות. Tosafot. You see it? גרסת ר"ח אשם מצורע שנשפך דמו קודם
מתן בהונות. girsa d'Rach asham metzora she-nishpach damo kodem matan behonot. Okay.
So it's a basically a very parallel case, which is that the
תורה Torah says you שחט shacht the אשם, asham, it actually doesn't
say by the מצורע metzora you sprinkle the blood of the אשם
asham on the מזבח mizbe-ach but presumably you do, that's what you
do by all קרבנות. korbanot. And then you take some of the
blood and you do similar things, you put it on the ear,
on the thumb, and on the toe. Let's say between putting the
blood on the מזבח mizbe-ach and doing the בהונות behonot the blood
spilled, right? So it's a similar case, you're in the middle of
the process with the blood and the blood spilled. How much do
you have to go back to the beginning or not go back
to the beginning? Okay. Is that clear the scenario just described? Okay.
So אשם מצורע asham metzora with גרסת ר"ח girsa d'Rach גרסה שנשפך
דמו, girsa she-nishpach damo, שנשפך דמו קודם
מתן בהונות. she-nishpach damo kodem matan behonot. It spilled before the stuff
on the ear or the toe after you did the blood on
the מזבח. mizbe-ach. פלוגתא דרבי מאיר ורבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון. pelugta de-Rabbi
Meir ve-Rabbi Elazar ve-Rabbi Shimon. It's the same debate. רבי מאיר דאמר
יביא אחר ויתחיל בתחילה. Rabbi Meir de-amar yavi acher ve-yatchil ba-techilah. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says you have to start again at the beginning.
הכא נמי יביא אחר וישחוט. hacha nami yavi acher ve-yishchot. You have
to start again at the beginning. Presumably he would not say the
putting of the blood on the מזבח mizbe-ach and on the ear
are separate units. You could have said those were separate units. But
they say no, that would all be one unit and if it
spilled in the middle start again at the beginning. ורבי אלעזר ורבי
שמעון שאומרים ממקום שפסק משם הוא מתחיל. ve-Rabbi Elazar ve-Rabbi Shimon she-omerim
mi-makom she-pasak misham hu matchil. They say pick up where you left
off. הכא, hacha, here it becomes interesting, אין לו תקנה. ein lo
takanah. You're stuck. Why are you stuck? Why not שחט shacht another
אשם asham and pick up where you left off? So we're going
to see the reason is because the תורה Torah says—because the תורה
Torah says—אותו. oto.
So ורבנן ve-rabbanan because it says
אותו. oto. אחד אשם. echad asham. So it says one אשם. asham.
So since it says one אשם, asham, you're really stuck. Because it
says look, you were sprinkling the blood, you did it on the
מזבח, mizbeiach, it spilled before you got to the ears. So they
say you have to pick up where you left off, but it
says only one אשם. asham. And if you were to try to
pick up where you left off, you'd have two אשמות. ashamot. So
that becomes now an interesting case where you get stuck in the
middle. I have a sense people are losing me. Are people with
me here? More or less? Okay. You mean a parallel situation? Yeah.
You spilled the blood of the אשם, asham, you did the מזבח,
mizbeiach, you didn't do the בהונות. behonot. It's like spilling in the
middle of a process. Normally רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar v'Rabbi
Shimon say you pick up where you left off. Here they're saying
you need to pick up where you left off, but you're not
allowed to. Because it says one אשם. asham. So you're totally stuck.
You can't go to the beginning because then you'd be repeating, you're
not allowed to repeat. You can't pick up in the middle because
it says one אשם. asham. So you're stuck. Okay. So אין לו
תקנה. ein lo takana. So מתיב ליה רב חסדא, metiv lei Rav
Chisda, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda asked him this, והאותו כתיב, ve'ha'oto
ketiv, but one minute, the פסוק pasuk says והקריב אותו לאשם, ve'hikriv
oto l'asham, so which means that even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir should
agree that you can't pick up where, hold on one minute,
I'm trying to remember what the point was by the אותו. oto.
Just one
second. Right, meaning that since it says אותו, oto, they should at
least agree here. Yeah.
Hold on just one second, I'm sorry, I just lost my place
here. Right, so
meaning, how can you say that according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
you should be allowed to bring another one and start again at
the beginning if it says אותו, oto, which should say that even
according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you should only be limited to
one.
And read it logistically with it then, right?
Yeah, exactly. So then it says קשיא. kashya. Okay, let's just read
a little bit more, I know it's towards the end but I
want to just get through this point right now. תניא כוותיה דרבי
יוחנן, Tanya kevata de'Rabbi Yochanan, אשם מצורע ששחטו שלא לשמו asham metzora
she'shachato she'lo lishmo או שלא נתן מדמו לגבי בהונות. o she'lo natan
mi'damo lgabei behonot.
So according to תוספות Tosafot the focus is on the second part,
that it's the blood spilled before you got to the בהונות. behonot.
הרי זה עולה לגבי מזבח harei ze oleh lgabei mizbeiach וטעון נסכים.
ve'taun nesechim. So you put it on the מזבח, mizbeiach, that you
do, because the animal itself is כשר, kasher, because the blood was
put on the מזבח. mizbeiach. But וצריך אשם אחר להכשירו. ve'tzarich asham
acher l'hachshiro. Okay,
but you need now to do another אשם, asham, you pick up,
you bring another אשם asham in order to go through the process.
It's too late and it's getting too confusing, we'll have to pick
up here tomorrow.